Finding Aid for Wilson Ornithological Society records, 1887-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Wilson Ornithological Society records 1887-2003 1960s-2002
Wilson Ornithological Society.
7 linear feet
0341 Bn 2
Miscellaneous correspondence, membership material, constitution, agreement with the University of Michigan; also presidents' files, 1997-2002.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group came from the Society (donor no. 9303 ) beginning in 2003.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Wilson Ornithological Society, founded in 1888, is a world-wide organization of nearly 2500 people who share a curiosity about birds. Named in honor of Alexander Wilson, the Father of American Ornithology, the Society publishes a quarterly journal of ornithology, The Wilson Journal of Ornithology, and holds annual meetings.
Perhaps more than any other biological science, ornithology has been advanced by the contributions of persons in other chosen professions. The Wilson Society recognizes the unique role of the serious amateur in ornithology. Fundamental to its mission, the Society has distinguished itself with a long tradition of promoting a strong working relationship among all who study birds. Each year the Wilson Society awards a number of small grants for ornithological research.
In addition to receiving The Wilson Journal of Ornithology four times a year, and being served by the Josselyn Van Tyne Memorial Library, members also receive the bimonthly Ornithological Newsletter and access to The Flock (an online directory of ornithologists), resources produced by the Ornithological Societies of North America (OSNA), of which the Wilson Ornithological Society is one of six member societies. The Ornithological Newsletter provides news about the member Societies, requests for assistance from researchers, professional positions, worldwide opportunities for field assistants (both paid and volunteer), graduate student positions and support, information on grants, new publications, scientific bird meetings, and news of members.
The headquarters and library of the WOS are in the Bird Division of the University of Michigan Museum of Zoology. The mailing address is Wilson Ornithological Society, Museum of Zoology, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI 48109-1079 USA.
The record group consist of a scattering of early records from the 19th century, including some correspondence and a notebook from the Wilson Ornithological Club, Cambridge, Mass. The bulk of the records date from the 1960s and consist of files of various individuals holding office within the organization as president or in some other position.
Subjects:
Wilson Ornithological Society.; Ornithology--Societies, etc.
- Earlier records
  - Correspondence, 1888-1897 (Box 1)
  - Notebook of the Wilson Ornithological Club, Cambridge, Mass, 1887-1889 (Box 1)
  - Wilson Ornithological Chapter of the Agassiz Association, 1889-1900 (Box 1)
  - Constitution (including revision), 1930 and 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - Agreement with the University of Michigan, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1944 (Box 1)
- Presidents' and other officers' files
  - Edward H. Burtt, Jr., 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    (includes earlier files from predecessors; also Burtt's file as WOS first vice president)
  - Edward H. Burtt, Jr., 1997-1998 (Box 2)
  - William E. Davis, Jr., 2001-2002 (Box 2)
    (also includes some earlier files)
  - William E. Davis, Jr., 2001-2002 (Box 3)
  - John Kricher, 1999-2000 (Box 3)
  - Edward H. Burtt, Jr. (Box 4)
  - Keith Bildstein (Box 4)
  - Pershing Hofslund, 1960s-1970s (Box 5)
  - Clait E. Braun, 1970s-1998 (Box 6)
  - Clait E. Braun (cont.) (Box 7)
  - Richard Banks (Box 7)